Guide to the Roman Gulʹ Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
The first box contains a miscellany of evaluations, suggestions, and criticism of the programs and scripts. The scripts for the Voice of America occupy two boxes. Subjects dicussed include: Stalin's article praising Trotsky, Stalin's speech at the Teheran conference about the American war industry, Gromyko's speech, the first displaced persons transport arriving at New York on June 25, 1948, Soviet aggression in Finland, and American help for the hungry in the Soviet Union in 1921-22.
The Radio Liberty scripts fill eight boxes. Supplemental information can be found in Series VII, Box 86, folder 2069, under "American Committee." Gul' grouped the scripts in eleven series under the headings: "Nashe demokraticheskoe nasledstvo" (Our Democratic Heritage), "Rossiia na zapade" (Russia in the West), "Sovremennaia russkaia literatura" (Russian Contemporary Literature), "Zaria svobody" (Dawn of Liberty), "Zarubezhnaia russkaia literatura" (Russian Émigré Literature), "O svobode naroda" (About The Liberty of the Nation), "Oktiabrskaia kontr-revoliutsiia" (October Counter-Revolution), "Pis'ma na rodinu" (Letters to the Homeland), "Problemy ideologii" (Ideology Problems), "Russkaia svobodnaia mysl'" (Russian Free Thoughts), and "Zapretnye stranitsy" (Forbidden Pages). Most of the scripts were written by Gul'. Subjects discussed include freedom of the press, freedom of expression, liberalism and Russian liberals, Russian democrats, Soviet and émigré magazines and newspapers, Soviet propaganda, strikes and the right to strike, peasant questions, dictatorship and legality, Russian and Soviet writers, poets, émigré inventors, scientists, philosophers, composers, and musicians, the Duma, excerpts of articles from Novyi zhurnal, historical events, the NKVD, the Soviet judicial system, attorneys and courts, political trials, the October Revolution, Lenin, and Kerensky's provisional government.
Series IV, Printed Works (Boxes 72-76), contains fifty-seven books and pamphlets. They are all in Russian, except for one in English and another in French. The works were published between 1879 and 1964 and come from the private collection of Gul' and his wife. Prominent authors represented in the series include IU. P. Annenkov, Maksim Gorky, I. S. Turgenev, V. Voskresenskii, and I. A. Sikorskii.
Serials (Boxes 77-78), include twenty-eight alphabetically arranged titles published between 1913 and 1966. The most valuable are: Zhizn', Sovremennye zapiski, Posev, and a complete set of Narodnaia pravda. The purpose of Narodnaia pravda was to attract the support of the "new" Russian emigrants in the battle against communism.
The clippings (around 640, sometimes extremely fragile items, in Boxes 79-81) include articles on a variety of subjects, such as biographies, necrologies, book reviews, and "Vlasovtsy," Russian political organizations (RND, Liga, SONR). They are mostly in Russian, but folders 1933-34 contain clippings in other languages.
Series V, Photographs, is housed in three boxes. Boxes 82-83 contain photographs of individuals (43 items) and of groups (48). Box 84 houses five photocopies of "Portraits," thirteen of "Places and Others," and one album. The album, containing 22 photographs (21 with prisoners, and one view) of a Czarist labor camp in Siberia, belonged to V. M. Zenzinov. A terrorist in his youth, Zenzizov was a member of the Socialist Revolutionary party who financially supported the Bolshevik Revolution, but in 1919 he emigrated. Included are autographed photographs of I. S. Turgenev and Z. N. Gippius, photos of émigré writers and poets (G. V. Ivanov, D. S. Merezhkovskii, V. L. Korvin-Piotrovskii, IU. V. Ofrosimov and I. V. Odoevtseva), of editors of Novaia russkaia kniga (A. S. IAshchenko), of Nakanune (B. Diushen), and of Russkaia mysl' (S. A. Vodov), of Soviet writers and poets (K. A. Fedin, N. N. Nikitin, B. A. Pilniak, and E. Evtushenko), of A. N. Tolstoi (who returned to the Soviet Union), and of R. Khodziev, adjutant of Gen. L. G. Kornilov. A photograph of M. A. Kharuzin, the murderer of the Gen. Romanovskii, is housed in Series VII, Box 86, folder 2075.
One box of Gul's Personal Papers comprise Series VI, which includes documents in German related to Gul's 1961 efforts to obtain indemnification from the West German government for his confinement in 1933; correspondence in English and French related to his temporary employment with London Film Productions, Inc. in 1936-37; correspondence with the Office international Nansen pour réfugiés in Paris concerning visas that would allow his family in Berlin to emigrate to France; some bills from the International Broadcasting Division of the United States Department of State for Gul's script-writing for the Voice of America; and some correspondence and documents in Russian related to his Masonic episode. The series also contains a few reviews of Gul's works, a handful of articles, and his 1935 curriculum vitae written in Paris.
Series VII, Special Files, contains two boxes of papers on a variety of subjects. The first folder concerns the American Committee for the Freedom for the Peoples of the USSR, Inc. Chartered in Delaware in 1948, this group was closely associated with the Russian political organizations and Radio Liberty in opposition to the Soviet Union and is of paramount importance to the Roman Gul' papers.
Box 86, folders 2070-75, "The Cases," concern Gul's personal relationships with others and his eagerness to collect as much information as possible about certain people. There are letters, answers, testimonies, and clippings about D. J. Dallin (problems Liga/AC/SONR); Sergei Gavlich (supposed Cheka agent); and the case of Gul'/Mel'gunov/TSurikov. One folder contains information about A. F. Kerenskii. Another contains documents about M. A. Kharuzin, the murderer of the Gen. I. P. Romanovskii. The next twenty-six folders contain the curricula vitae of such individuals as D. J. Dallin, N. N. Evreinov, I. A. Kurganov, V. Lebedev, and V. B. Stankevich. Folder 2106 contains sketches of anti-communist posters drawn by N. F. Mishatkin.
The Roman Gul' Papers cover a wide range of issues and contain a great deal of information on Gul's life, his activities, friendships, and difficult relationships with others. The achievements, failures, and thoughts of Russian émigrés, the history of Russian emigration, and the development and growth of Novyi zhurnal are documented. The papers are also an important resource for the history of Russian political organizations, their activities, their goals, the reasons for their failure to unify, and their connections to the American Committee. The writings provide considerable insight into Russian émigré literary and political thought, opinion, and ideas, and the materials selected or rejected for publication reveal Gul's own editorial preferences, taste, and political views.
Appendix I: Gul's Published Books
Azef. Translated from the Russian by Mirra Ginsburg. Garden City, N. Y.: Doubleday, 1962.
Azef; istoricheskii roman. [Izd. 3-e]. New York: Most, 1959. Published originally under title: General Bo.
Azef; istoricheskii roman. Izd. 4., ispr. New York: Most, 1974.
Azeff. Translated from Russian into Japanese by Noboru Kanzaki. Tokyo: Kavado Shabo, 1960. (2 eds.)
Belye po chernomu. Moskva: Gos. izd-vo, 1928.
Belye po chernomu. Moskva: Gos. izd-vo, 1928. Microfilm copy (negative) made by the Joint University Libraries Photoduplication Service [1971]
Chitaia "Avgust chetyrnadtsatogo" A. I. Solzhenitsyna. New York: Izd-vo Rausen Publishers, 1971
Dzerzhinskii. (Menzhinskii-Peters-Latsis-IAgoda.) Parizh: [Imp. de Navarre, c1936]
Dzerzhinskii; nachalo terrora. Izd. 2., ispr. New York: Most, 1974.
[Dzerzhinskii. French] Les maetres de la TchTka; histoire de la terreur en U.R.S.S., 1917-1938. Traduit du russe. Paris: Les +ditions de France, c1938.
General Bo, roman. [Izd. 1-e] Berlin: Petropolis [1929] 2v.
General Bo; roman. Izd. 2-e. Berlin: Petropolis [1929] 1v.
General Bo. Authorized translation by L. Zarine; ed. by Stephen Graham. [1st Eng. ed.] London: Ernest Benn Limited, 1930.
[General Bo. English] Provocateur. A Historical Novel of the Russian Terror. Authorized translation by L. Zarine. ed. with an introduction by Stephen Graham. New York: Harcourt, Brace and Co., 1931.
[General Bo. French] Lanceurs de bombes. Azef. Taduit par N. Guterman. [Paris]: Gallimard, 1930.
[General Bo. German] Boris Sawinkow; der Roman eines Terroristen. Autorisierte _bersetzung von F. Frisch. Berlin; Wien; Leipzig: Paul Zsolnay Verlag, 1930.
[General Bo. Lithuanian] Sprogstancios Bombos. Romanas. Kaunas: P. Kezinaitis, 1932.
[General Bo. Polish] General Bo; powiesc. Przelozyla z rosyjskiego Halina Pilichowska. Warszawa: Towarystwo Wydawnicze "R=j", 1933.
[General Bo. Polish] General Bo .[Z rosyjskiego tlumaczyla Halina Pilichowska. 1. wyd. Warszawa:] Ksiazka i wiedza, 1958. (Reprinted without the author's knowledge and approval).
[General Bo. Spanish] Los lanzadores de bombas. Azef. Savinkov. Traducido por Amando Lazaro y Ros. Madrid: Zevs Editorial, 1931.
IA unes Rossiiu: apologiia emigratsii. New York: Most, 1981- Contents: t.1. "Rossiia v Germanii". t.2. "Rossiia vo Frantsii".
K voprosu ob "avtokefalii". Pis'mo A. I. Solzhenitsyna Patriarchu Pimenu. New York: Izd. Avtora, 1972.
Kon' ryzhii. New York: Izd-vo im. Chekhova, 1952.
Kon' ryzhii; avtobiografia. Izd. 2-oe. New York: Most, 1975.
[Kon' Ryzhii. Spanish] El caballo rojo. [Traduccion directa del ruso por Agustfn Puig. Barcelona: Editorial Planeta, 1962]
Kotovskii -- anarkhist-marshal. Izd. 2. New York: Most, 1975. Photoreproduction of a chapter from the author's "Voroshilov... " published in Berlin in 1933[?] by Parabola.
[Krasnye marshaly] Voroshilov, Budennyi, Bliukher, Kotovskii. [Berlin]: Izd-vo Parabola [1933?]
[Krasnye marshaly] Voroshilov, Budennyi, Bliukher, Kotovskii. [Berlin]: Izd-vo Parabola [1934]. Microfilm (negative) made by the Joint University Libraries Photoduplication Service [1971]
[Krasnye marshaly. Czech] Rudf marsÃŸlovT: Vorosilov, Budenny, Blncher, Kotovskij. Prel. V. Foch a Oleg Vojtfsek. V Praze: A. Neubert, 1934.
[Krasnye marshaly. Czech] Rudf marsÃŸlovT: Vorosilov, Budenny, Blncher, Kotovskij. Prel. V. Foch a Oleg Vojtisek. V Praze: A. Neubert, 1934. Microfilm (negative) 4 sheets
[Krasnye marshaly. Finnish] Punaiset Marsalkat. Svomentanut K. M. Wallenius. Otava: HelsingissS Kustannusosa-Keyhti÷, 1936.
[Krasnye marshaly. French] Les grands chefs de l'armTe soviTtique; traduit du russe par J. Civel. Paris: +ditions Berger-Levrault, 1935.
[Krasnye marshaly. French] Les grands chefs de l'armTe soviTtique; traduit du russe por J. Civel. Paris: +ditions Berger-Levrault, 1935. Photocopy. New Haven, Yale University Library, 1976.
[Krasnye marshaly. German] Die roten MarschSlle. Berlin: Obelisk Verlag, 1933.
[Krasnye marshaly. Latvian] Kaujas organizScijas generSlis, romans. Ar autora atlauju tulkojis Valdis Grdvins. [Riga: A. Gulbis], 1930.
[Krasnye marshaly. Polish] Czerwoni dow=dcy. Warszawa: Towarystwo Wydawnicze "R=j", 1934.
[Krasnye marshaly. Swedish] De R÷da Morskalkarna. Helsingfors: S÷derstr÷m Co., 1936.
Ledianoi pokhod. (S Kornilovym). Berlin: S. Efron, 1921.
Ledianoi pokhod. (S Kornilovym). Predislovie N. L. Meshcherakova. Moskva; Petrograd: Gos. izd-vo, 1923.
Lenin i "Arkhipelag GULag. N'iu Iork, 1973. Ottisk stat'i iz 115 knigi Novogo zhurnala.
Odvukon'; sovetskaia i emigrantskaia literatura. New York: Most, 1973.
Odvukon' dva. New York: Izd-vo "Most", 1982.
Oranienburg; chto ia videl v gitlerovskom kontsentratsionnom lagere. Paris [1937]
Pol v tvorchestve. razbor proizvedenii Andreia Belogo. Berlin: Manfred, 1923.
Pol v tvorchestve. razbor proizvedenii A. Belogo. Berlin: Manfred, 1923. Microfilm copy (negative) made by the Joint University Libraries Photoduplication Service [1971]
Skif; roman. Berlin: Petropolis [1931]
Skif v Evrope, Bakunin i Nikolai I. New York: Izd-vo Most, 1958. Rev. ed. of Skif published in 1931.
[Skif] Bakunin; istoricheskaia khronika. Izd. 3. New York: Most, 1974. First ed. published in 1931 under title: Skif. Rev. ed. published in 1958 under title: Skif v Evrope.
Solzhenitsyn: stat'i. New York: Most, 1976, c1975.
Tovarishch Ivan; p'esa v 3-kh aktakh i 9-i kartinakh. New York: Most, 1968.
[Tovarisch Ivan] Comrade Ivan; a play in 3 acts. Translated by Elizabeth Reynolds Hapgood. New York: Most, 1969.
Tukhachevskii, krasnyi marshal. Berlin: Izd-vo "Parabola" [1932]
Tukhachevskii, krasnyi marshal. Berlin: Izd-vo "Parabola" [1932]. Microfilm (negative) made by the Joint University Libraries Photoduplication Service [1971]
[Tukhachevskii. French] Toukhatchevsky, MarTchal rouge. Traduit du russe par J. Civel. Paris: Edgar MalfFre, 1935.
V rozsieian'i sushchie; povest' iz zhizni emigratsii, 1920-1921. Berlin: Manfred, 1923.
V rozsieian'i sushchie; povest' iz zhizni emigratsii,1920-1921. Berlin: Manfred, 1923. Microfilm (negative) made by the Joint University Libraries Photoduplication Service [1971]
Zhizn' na fuksa. Moskva; Leningrad: Gos. izd-vo, 1927.
Zhizn' na fuksa. Moskva: Gos. izd-vo, 1927. Microfilm copy.
Appendix II: The American Committee and Radio Liberty Changes in Name
(covering only the Roman Gul' Papers' years)
1951 Jan 19 American Committee for Freedom of the People of the USSR, Inc. is chartered in Delaware as a private corporation
May 22 American Committee for the Liberation of the Peoples of Russia, Inc.
1953 Mar 16 American Committee for Liberation from Bolshevism, Inc.
1956 Sep 5 Radio Liberation Committee, Inc.
1964 Jan Radio Liberty Committee, Inc.
1953 Mar 1- 56 Radio Liberation from Bolshevism
1956-63 Radio Liberation Committee
1964 -Radio Liberty Committee (for radio operations, simply used Radio Liberty)
Appendix III: Abbreviations Used
DP - displaced persons, primarily after WWII
Liga - Liga bor'by za narodnuiu svobodu
League - League of Struggle for Peoples Freedom
Mel'gunov group - Soiuz bor'by za svobodu Rossii
NKVD - Narodnyi kommisariat vnutrennikh del (People's Commissariat for Internal Affairs)=secret service
NTS - Natsional'no-trudovoi soiuz
RND - Rossiikoe narodnoe dvizhenie
SBONR - Soiuz bor'by za osvobozhdenie narodov Rossii
SONR - Soviet osvobozhdeniia narodov Rossii
Separated Materials
Books listed in Series IV. Printed Works, formerly housed in boxes 72-76, and the bulk of the serials formerly housed in boxes 77-78, have been removed and individually cataloged. They are accessible in Orbis, the Yale University Library Catalog.
Novyĭ zhurnal; Authors, Russian -- 20th Century; Adamovich, Georgiĭ, 1892-1972; Annenkov, I͡Uriĭ, 1889-1974; Aldanov, Mark Aleksandrovich, 1886-1957; Balʹmont, Konstantin Dmitrievich, 1867-1942; Berberova, N. (Nina), 1901-1993; Berezov, Rodion, 1896-1988; Berlin, P. A. (Pavel Abramovich), 1877-; Bogatyrchuk, F. P., 1892-; Bunin, Ivan Alekseevich, 1870-1953; Chinnov, Igorʹ; Czapski, Józef, 1896-1993; Dallin, David J., 1889-1962; Fessenko, Tatiana Sviatenko, 1915-1995; Gippius, Z. N. (Zinaida Nikolaevna), 1869-1945; Gulʹ, Roman, 1896-1986; Ivanov, Georgiĭ, 1894-1958; Ivanov, V. I. (Vi͡acheslav Ivanovich), 1866-1949; Ivask, I︠U︡riĭ, 1907-1986; Karpovich, Michael, 1888-1959; Kerensky, Aleksandr Fyodorovich, 1881-1970; Kravchenko, Victor, 1905-1966; Kurganov, I. A. (Ivan Alekseevich); Kuskova, Ekaterina; Losskiĭ, N. O. (Nikolaĭ Onufrievich), 1870-1965; Mackiewicz, Józef, 1902-1985; Margolin, I︠U︡liĭ, 1900-1971; Melʹgunov, S. P. (Sergeĭ Petrovich), 1879-1956; Merezhkovsky, Dmitry Sergeyevich, 1865-1941; Narokov, Nikolaĭ; Nicolaevsky, Boris I., 1887-1966; Nilʹskiĭ, Mikhail; Odoevt︠s︡eva, Irina, 1895-1990; Pletnev, R. (Rostislav), 1903-1985; Rannit, Aleksis; Remizov, Alekseĭ, 1877-1957; Rosimov, G.; Rzhevskiĭ, Leonid, 1905-1986; Shmelev, I. S. (Ivan Sergeevich), 1873-1950; Shteppa, Konstantin, 1896-1958; Stanka, Vladas, 1884-1968; Stepun, Fedor, 1884-1965; Struve, Gleb, 1898-1985; Tauber, Ekaterina; Tschežewskij, Dmitrij, 1894-1977; T͡Svetaeva, Marina, 1892-1941; Ulʹi͡anov, N. (Nikolaĭ), 1904-1985; Valentinov, N. (Nikolaĭ), 1879-1964; Veĭdle, V., 1895-1979; Vishni︠a︡k, M. V. (Mark Venʹi︠a︡minovich), 1883-1977; Zaĭt︠s︡ev, Boris, 1881-1972; Zaret︠s︡kiĭ, Nikolaĭ Vasilʹevich, 1876-1959 or 1960; Zenzinov, V. (Vladimir), 1880-1953; Zlobin, Vladimir, 1894-1967; Voice of America (Organization)
- Correspondence, 1881-1966; Series I; 9.5; (26 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, fills Boxes 1-26. The correspondence is divided into three subseries: Incoming (Boxes 1-17), alphabetically arranged by author, Outgoing (Boxes 18-23), alphabetically arranged by recipient, and By Third Party (Boxes 24-26), alphabetically arranged by author. Unidentified correspondence is located in Boxes 17 (folders 403-09), 23 (folders 544-47), and 26 (folders 574-77). "Letter" general files contain correspondences of fewer than ten items.
  - INCOMING
    - "A" general, 1934-65 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
    - Abramskii, IAkov Khatskevich, 1957-63, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Adamovich, Georgii, 1955-65 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Aksarin, Mikhail Ivanovich, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Alcheev, Ivan Ivanovich, 1948-49 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Series III, Subject Files, Pol. organizations: RND, Box 52, folder 58
    - Aldanov, Mark Aleksandrovich, 1946-56 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Alekseeva, Lidiia Alekseevna, 1956-64 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Andreev, Dimitrii Ivanovich, 1947-53 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Anin, David Sergeevich, [1949?]-65 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - Annenkov, IUrii Pavlovich, 1956-65, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Arkhangel'skii, Valerian Petrovich, 1947-50 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Aronson, Gregor, 1949-65 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "B" general, 1933-64, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17-24)
    - Balitskii, Sergei Grigorovich, 1949-53 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Beklemishev, Anatolii Petrovich, 1950-54 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Berberova, Nina Nikolaevna, 1948-64, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 27-29)
    - Berezov, Rodion, 1952-63 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
    - Berger, IAkov Iosifovich, 1956-64 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Berlin, Pavel Abramovich, 1947-50, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
    - Bertensson, Sergei, 1957-61 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Bervi, Ol'ga Vladimirovna, 1952-54 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Bondarenko, Vladimir Ivanovich, 1951-55 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Buldakova, Anna Grigor'evna, 1928-31, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37-39)
      See also: Oversize, Box 88, folder 2122
    - Bunin, Ivan, Alekseevich, 1946-53 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Bunina, V. N. (Vera Nikolaevna), 1953-61, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Butenko, Vasilii Fedos'evich, 1947-49 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Bychek, IAkov Konstantinovich, 1950-65, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 43-48)
    - Bystrovskii, Konstantin Mikhailovich, 1949-50 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - "C" general [including Charchoune, Serge], 1936-64, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 50-51)
    - Camus, Albert, [1949] (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Chamberlain, William Henry, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Chavchavadze, Pavel Aleksandrovich, 1951-[54] (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Chekhonin, Mikhail Georgievich, 1952-61 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Chekhov Publishing House (New York), 1953-55 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Chinnov, Igor' Vladimirovich, 1951-65 (Box 3, Folder 57-59)
    - Cholovskii, Nikifor Avvakumovich, 1950-60, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Chyzhevs'kyi Dmytro, 1952-65 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Civel, J., 1935, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Comité des Zemstvos, 1945-49 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Czapski, Joseph Georgievich, 1947-49 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Czapski, Maria, 1948-55 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - "D" general, 1935-64, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 65-68)
    - Dallin, David J., 1947-62, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 69-70)
    - Denike, IUrii Petrovich, 1950-60, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Diamandi, Ivan, 1950-60, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Dikov, IUrii Vasil'evich, 1948-52 (Box 4, Folder 73-77)
      See also: Series III, Subjects Files, Pol. Organizations: RND, Box 52, folder 58
    - Dolin, Georgii, 1951-56 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Domger, Liudvig Leopol'dovich
      See: Domherr, Ludwig L. Box 4, folder 79
    - Domherr, Ludwig L., 1954-58 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Dostoevskaia, Ekaterina Petrovna, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Doubleday and Company, 1938-63 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Durakov, Aleksei Petrovich, 1935-38 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Dvinov, Boris L'vovich, 1947-60 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - "E" general, 1935-64 (Box 4, Folder 84-85)
    - Editorial Planeta (Barcelona, Spain), 1954-62 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Elagin, IU[rii Borisovich]
      See: Jelagin, Juri, Box 6, folder 139
    - El'kin, Boris Ivanovich, 1934-47 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Evreinova, Anna Aleksandrovna
      See: Kashina-Evreinova, Anna Aleksandrovna, Box 7, folder 161
    - Ezerskii, N. [F.], 1931-32 (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - "F" general [including Filippov, Boris Andreevich], 1934-64, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 89-90)
    - Fessenko, Andrew V. and Tatiana, 1948-65 (Box 4, Folder 91-95)
    - "G" general [including Ginsburg, Mirra], 1930-64, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 96-101)
    - Gaevskii, Valentin Grigor'evich, 1950-54 (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - Gazdanov, Gaito, 1945-65, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - Glebov, Ivan Andreevich, 1959-63 (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - Gofman, Modest Liudvigovich
      See: Hofmann, Modeste, Box 4, folder 117
    - Goldwin, Fedor Ivanovich, 1951-52 (Box 5, Folder 105)
      See also: Series III, Subject Files, Pol. Organiations: RND, Box 52, folder 58
    - Golubowski, Aleksy, 1935-64, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 106)
    - Gorb, Fedor Ivanovich
      See: Kubanskii, Fedor, Box 8, folder 180
    - Gorokhova, Kl., 1952-59 (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - Grigor'ev, Ivan Matveeich, 1951-54 (Box 5, Folder 108)
    - Grinberg, Roman Nikolaevich, 1948-64 (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - Grossman, Vladimir, 1948-50 (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - Grudin, Vladimir Vladimirovich and Grudina, A, 1950-54 (Box 5, Folder 111)
    - Gul', Ol'ga Sergeevna, [1920-21] (Box 5, Folder 112)
    - Gurvich, Abram [Rafailovich], 1955-64 (Box 5, Folder 113)
    - Guzenko, Igor', 1954-55 (Box 5, Folder 114)
    - "H" general, 1913-64, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 115)
    - Hapgood, Elizabeth (Reynolds), 1947-64 (Box 5, Folder 116)
    - Hofmann, Modeste, 1954-58 (Box 5, Folder 117)
    - "I" general, 1923-64, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 118-20)
    - IAkovlev, Boris Aleksandrovich, 1949-52 (Box 6, Folder 121)
    - IAtsevich, Aleksei Viktorovich, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 122)
    - Il'in, Iosif Sergeevich, 1958-65 (Box 6, Folder 123-24)
    - International Refugee Organization, 1948-51 (Box 6, Folder 125)
    - Ioann, Abp. of San Francisco and Western United States, 1960-65 (Box 6, Folder 126)
    - IUreva, Zoia Iosifovna, 1951-64, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 127)
    - Ivanov, Boris, 1947-64 (Box 6, Folder 128)
    - Ivanov, Georgii Vladimirovich and Ivanova, Irina Vladimirovna, 1953-58, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 129-34)
      See also: Odoevtseva, Irina Vladimirovna, Box 10, folder 239
    - Ivanov, Pavel, 1950-53 (Box 6, Folder 135)
    - Ivask, George, 1950-65 (Box 6, Folder 136-37)
    - "J" general, 1951-62 (Box 6, Folder 138)
    - Jelagin, Juri, 1949-54 (Box 6, Folder 139)
    - "K" general [including Kravchenko, Viktor Andreevich and Kultura (Jerzy Giedroyc)], 1933-64, n.d. (Box 6-7, Folder 140-48)
    - Kamkin, Viktor Petrovich, 1957-64 (Box 7, Folder 149)
    - Kannak, E., 1953-63 (Box 7, Folder 150)
    - Kanzaki, Naboru, 1959-64 (Box 7, Folder 151)
    - Karakatenko, Arkadii Gerasimovich, 1948-49 (Box 7, Folder 152)
    - Karpovich, Michael, 1946-59, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 153-60)
    - Kashina-Evreinova, Anna Aleksandrovna, 1953-65, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 161)
    - Keisermann, Sinaida, 1948-50 (Box 7, Folder 162)
    - Kerenskii, Aleksandr Fedorovich, 1949-51 (Box 7, Folder 163)
    - Khadzhiev, Razak Bek, Khan, 1953-65 (Box 7, Folder 164-65)
    - Khomiakov, Gennadii Andreevich, 1955-64 (Box 7, Folder 166)